Guide to the Herbert Lionel Matthews Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series V: Personal, 1909-1970s
  This brief series contains a disparate array of documents, papers and photographs about Matthews' life within and beyond his career as a journalist. This section includes materials related to Matthews' life-long interest in Italian history, culture, and thought, begun while a student at Columbia University, such as files on Columbia professor Dino Bigongiari and Matthews' support for the university's Casa Italiana in the 1960s. This section also holds various personal documents such as passports and journalist identification cards from Matthews' entire career as a journalist. Photographs, including photographs of Matthews in World War I, and a folder of material regarding the work of Spanish artist Luis Quintanilla, who served the Republican government in the Spanish Civil War, also are included here.
  - Awards, 1950s (Box 29, Folder 7)
  - Bigongiari, Dino and Gladys, 1940s-1960s (Box 29, Folder 8)
  - Casa Italiana--Columbia University, 1960s (Box 29, Folder 9)
  - Documents--Passports and Press Passes, 1920s-1960s (Box 29, Folder 10)
  - Horoscope, 1945, undated (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Photographs, 1918-1970s (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Quintanilla, Luis, 1930s-1940s (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Soldier of Fortune--Book--Inscribed, 1909 (Box 36, Folder 3)
- Series VI: Writings, 1930s-1972
  This large series records the multitude of books, articles, and addresses written by Herbert L. Matthews, and some material written about Matthews, not otherwise found in previous sections of the Matthews papers. Included are manuscripts, and often correspondence and notes for, and reviews of, his books: Two War and More to Come (1938), Fruits of Fascism (1943), Education of a Correspondent (1946), Assignment to Austerity (1950), The Yoke and the Arrows (1957), A World in Revolution (1971), and Half of Spain Died (1973). Also notable here is an unpublished manuscript written by Matthews in the 1970s, "Valediction"; and the transcript of an episode of the television show, "The Big Story," recounting Matthews' celebrated reports of March, 1955, concerning student politics under the Peronist dictatorship in Argentina.
  - Addresses, 1952 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Articles and Drafts, 1930s-1970s, (3 Folders) (Box 36, Folder 5 to 7)
  - Books--Manuscripts, 1938-1970s
    - Assignment to Austerity, 1950, (6 Folders) (Box 37, Folder 1 to 6)
    - The Education of a Correspondent, 1946 (1 of 4 Folders) (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - The Education of a Correspondent, 1946 (3 of 4 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 1 to 3)
    - Fruits of Fascism, 1943
      - Notes, 1939-1942 (2 of 3 Folders) (Box 38, Folder 4 to 5)
      - Notes, 1939-1942 (Box 39, Folder 1)
      - Reviews, 1943-1944 (Box 39, Folder f.2)
    - Half of Spain Died, 1973 (4 of 7 Folders) (Box 39, Folder 3 to 6)
    - Half of Spain Died, 1973 (4 of 7 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 1 to 3)
      - Reviews (Box 40, Folder 4)
    - "The Matthews Story," 1950s (Box 40, Folder 5)
    - A Newspaperman, 1970s (2 of 4 Folders) (Box 40, Folder 6 to 7)
    - A Newspaperman, 1970s (2 of 4 Folders) (Box 41, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Two Wars and More to Come, 1938 (Box 41, Folder 3)
    - Untitled--Spanish Civil War, undated (Box 41, Folder 4)
    - "Valediction," 1970s, (2 Folders) (Box 41, Folder 5 to 6)
    - A World in Revolution, 1971 (1 of 14 Folders) (Box 41, Folder 7)
    - A World in Revolution, 1971 (7 of 14 Folders) (Box 42, Folder 1 to 7)
      - A World in Revolution, 1971 (6 of 14 Folders) (Box 43, Folder 1 to 6)
        - Correspondence, 1967-1972 (Box 43, Folder 7)
        - Reviews, 1971, undated (Box 43, Folder f.8)
      - The Yoke and the Arrows, 1957, (2 Folders) (Box 44, Folder 1 to 2)
        - Volume--Annotated--and Critique, 1957, undated (Box 44, Folder 3)
      - Herbert L. Matthews--Subject, 1930s-1960s (Box 44, Folder 4)
      - Reviews, Book--Drafts, 1970s (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - Research Materials--Cuba and Spain
      - Cuba
        - Cuba: A Survey of World Cultures, Clifford R. Barnett and Wyatt MacGaffey 1962 (Box 44)
        - Cuba Sideshow, R. Hart Phillips, 1935 (Box 44)
        - Castro’s Revolution, Theodore Draper 1962 (Box 19)
      - Spain
        - "The Church and Franco Spain," William Ebenstein, 1960 (Box 19)
        - Documents on German Foreign Policy, 1918-1945-- Spain, 1950 (Box 19)
        - International Brigades, Vincent Brome, 1965 (Box 19)
        - Prelude to a War: The International Repercussions of the Spanish Civil War, P.A.M. van der Esch, 1951 (Box 19)
        - "Report of the Sub-Committee on the Spanish Question," United Nations, 1946 (Box 19)